One of the most common questions in the
comments on this channel is what about
equal weight index funds or some version
of that question. I promise you equal
weight index funds are not that
exciting, but people keep asking me the
question, so
here we are. Market capitalization
weighting, which is what typical index
funds do, assign index weights based on
each company's size.
An equal weighted index fund, as the
name implies, equally weights all of the
stocks in a market or market segment.
Equal weighting seems like the solution
to many of the perceived problems that
market capitalization weighted indexes
have today, like high valuations and
high levels of concentration in the top
stocks. Equal weighting has actually
outperformed cap weighting going back
decades as well, but it introduces its
own unique risks, costs, and
inefficiencies. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital, and
I'm going to tell you why I do not use
equal weighted index funds.
Equal weight index funds do look really
compelling right now. They don't have
the same level of concentration as a
market cap weighted index fund, and they
have a long track record of strong
performance. Even in live fund data
reflective of real fees and costs, the
Invesco S&P 500 equal weight ETF has
outperformed the S&P 500 for most of its
life since 2003 and for the full period
since its inception in 2003, just by a
hair, though. But before getting too
excited, it's important to understand
the tradeoffs and to give some context
to the past performance. I'm also going
to show you why I think the benefits of
equal weighting can be achieved more
efficiently without its associated
drawbacks. Let's start with some quick
background on equal weighted versus
market capitalization weighted indexes.
When you create a stock index, one of
the most fundamental questions that you
have to answer is how you're going to
weight the stocks in your index. Market
capitalization weighting means holding
stocks at their market capitalization
weights. Market capitalization is just
what the entire company is worth on the
stock market, like how much it would
cost to buy every single share of Apple
or Shopify. A larger company will make
up a larger portion of a market
capitalization weighted index than a
smaller company.
Make sense? Equal weighting, on the
other hand, assigns equal weights to
stocks regardless of their market
capitalization. These approaches can
result in significantly different
portfolios given the same set of stocks.
The logic of market capitalization or
market cap weighting is pretty simple.
The market has determined how much
weight each stock should have. This is
why market cap index investing is often
referred to as passive. You're passively
allowing the market to determine the
weights of the stocks that you own. It's
like letting water find its own level
instead of constantly trying to adjust
it yourself. The nice thing about this
is that it does not require you to make
decisions about how to weight the stocks
in your index. The weights just are.
Another benefit is that because the
index represents the market, it doesn't
need to be rebalanced frequently. As
stock prices evolve, the market
capitalization weighted index fund
evolves in exactly the same way as the
market without needing you to make
trades. One of the perceived problems
with market cap weighting is that it can
result in high weights in a relatively
small number of stocks, something we are
seeing an extreme version of in the US
market, at least relative to its own
history right now. This index
concentration kind of ebbs and flows
naturally over time as some businesses
become increasingly successful and earn
a larger share of the market. Market
concentration can seem concerning, but
the historical relationship between
market concentration and future market
returns has not been strong historically
in the US or in other countries around
the world. If we sort 10-year future US
stock market returns on their starting
level of market concentration, there's
really not much of a relationship there.
Many other countries have been and are
today more concentrated in the top
stocks in the index than the US market
is even today when it's more
concentrated than it has been in the
past. In any case, index concentration
is a current concern for many investors.
An equal weighted index, by
construction, by design, won't ever be
concentrated in a small number of stocks
in the same way that a market
capitalization weighted index can be,
but it will result in significant under
and overweights of stocks relative to
their market capitalization weights.
Now, this is an interesting question,
whether having a high weight in large
companies in a market cap weighted
portfolio is riskier than having large
overweights to smaller companies and
underweights to larger companies in an
equal weighted portfolio. The answer's
not black and white, but I think there's
a legitimate argument that the extreme
over and underweighting in an equal
weighted portfolio is actually riskier
than accepting concentration in larger
companies in a cap weighted portfolio.
This risk can show up in a couple of
different ways. One is in volatility.
Looking at an ETF tracking the S&P 500
and one tracking the S&P 500 equal
weight, the 15-year standard deviation,
a measure of how much variability there
is in index returns, is quite a bit
higher for the equal weight index than
for the market cap weighted index.
Volatility is not the only way to think
about risk. Another way to measure risk
is by exposure to certain types of
stocks that tend to move together. Some
stocks, like small cap and value stocks,
are theoretically priced as being
riskier by the market, and an equal
weight index has more exposure to these
types of stocks than a market cap
weighted one simply because smaller and
cheaper stocks make up a smaller portion
of the market. Equal weighting all
stocks results in a natural tilt towards
smaller and lower-priced stocks. This
speaks to one of the other perceived
benefits of equal weighting in the
current market environment. Stock
valuations in the US market are high
relative to their own history. High
current valuations do have a
relationship with lower future returns.
They're not perfectly predictive, but
there's something there. Due to its
natural tilt away from the largest and
highest priced stocks, an equal weighted
index will have a lower aggregate
valuation than a market cap weighted
index. We can see this now with the
price-to-earnings and price-to-book
ratios for an equal weighted S&P 500
fund being much lower than those for a
market cap weighted fund. Those
exposures to smaller and cheaper stocks
are not bad thing. I would actually
argue that they are a good thing when
they're done right. The problem is that
if you wanted to have exposure to these
types of stocks, there are probably more
efficient ways to get it. I'll explain
that in a minute. Equal weighted indexes
will also tend to have materially
different sector exposures compared to
market capitalization weighted indexes.
Sector over or underweights introduce a
whole other type of risk that most
investors probably want to avoid. Again,
looking at the pair of S&P 500 ETFs as
an example, we can see the sector
compositions are materially different
with a large underweight to technology
and overweight to industrials for the
equal weight index. If you want those
over and underweights because you have a
view on how those sectors are going to
perform in the future, I guess that's
fine, but sector bets tend to be really
hard to get right.
A lesser-known issue with equal weights
is the implications for rebalancing. One
issue is more frequent rebalancing. When
a smaller company gets larger, a market
cap weighted index does not need to do
anything, but an equal weight index
likely needs to sell down the position
back to equalize weights at its next
rebalancing. The same thing happens when
a large company gets smaller. For
example, this S&P 500 equal weight index
ETF has had average annual turnover more
than 10 times higher than a market cap
weighted S&P 500 ETF. Turnover comes
with implicit and explicit trading costs
that are ultimately borne by the fund
investors.
The other rebalancing issue is that
equal weighting is naturally a negative
momentum strategy. This is a big deal.
I'll I'll explain what it means.
Momentum is the extremely
well-documented phenomenon first
identified by Jegadeesh and Titman in
their landmark 1993 study that stocks
that have recently done well tend to
continue to do well for a time, and
those that have recently done poorly
tend to continue doing poorly for a
time.
Equal weight funds, to maintain their
equal weights, are always going to be
selling what has done well recently and
buying what has done poorly. If a stock
does well and gets bigger, its weight
will exceed its equal weight target, and
a stock that does poorly will fall below
its target. Maintaining equal weights,
then, means systematically trading
against momentum. We can show this with
a multi-factor regression. That's a
statistical test that shows us what's
driving a fund's returns. It's kind of
like a like a blood test for a fund. It
tells you what's in your system.
Looking again at the equal weight S&P
500, we can see that it loads positively
on the size factor and the value factor
and loads negatively on the momentum
factor. These factor loadings are all
statistically significant, meaning
they're real patterns, not just noise in
the data. This means that this fund has
more exposure to small cap and value
stocks than the market cap weighted
total market index, and that it's
trading in the opposite direction of
momentum. This is exactly what you would
expect based on the equal weighted
index's structure. It's naturally
overweight smaller and cheaper stocks
and underweight larger and more
expensive stocks, and it trades against
momentum systematically
by the way that it's designed.
Now, here's the big question. If you
want exposure to smaller and
lower-priced stocks, is equal weighting
the most efficient way to get there?
There are other investment strategies
that look a lot like index funds, but
don't strictly follow market cap
weights. For example, the Dimensional US
Core Equity One Fund has roughly similar
exposures to the small cap and value
factors as the equal weight S&P 500 ETF,
but rather than naively getting to these
exposures through equal weighting,
Dimensional is being super intentional
about targeting certain types of stocks.
This Dimensional fund has a net expense
ratio of 15 basis points, 0.15%,
compared to the equal weight S&P 500
ETFs 0.2%. It's basically a wash on fees
with a slight edge for Dimensional. I'm
going to talk about the long-term data
for this mutual fund, which is the the
one I'm talking about is a mutual fund,
that fund is only available through
financial advisors. That's just how
Dimensional distributes their products,
but just to make sure that this is
relevant for people watching, the same
strategy is available now through a
US-listed ETF that anybody can buy.
There's no no restrictions.
Uh so, Dimensional's intentional
approach shows up in a couple of
different ways. One is that they limit
the sector divergence from the market by
placing a cap on sector weight
differences to avoid taking on large
sector bets.
Another intentional difference is in
their treatment of momentum. So,
remember equal weighting is short
momentum. It's taking it's got negative
momentum exposure. Dimensional applies a
rule when they trade to avoid selling
recent winners and avoid buying recent
losers all else equal.
Dimensional funds are not index funds,
so they have the ability to do that type
of flexible trading.
They can decide to buy this stock
instead of that stock. Uh they'll
they'll buy the one that does not have
the the negative momentum exposure.
Another important way that their
intentional implementation shows up is
in the way that the portfolio turns
over, how how frequently the holdings
change. So, it's got similar tilts
towards smaller and lower-priced stocks
to the equal-weighted S&P 500 fund, but
the Dimensional fund has a really modest
turnover.
Now, a big part of the reason is that
while Dimensional is tilting towards
smaller and lower-priced stocks very
intentionally, they use market cap
weights as a starting point. So, they
start with take the market portfolio,
take like a a market cap-weighted index
fund, and then they're applying modest
tilts to get the exposures that they
want to smaller, lower-priced, more
profitable companies. So, this starting
with market cap weights minimizes
unnecessary deviations from market cap
weights, which then translates to less
aggressive rebalancing requirements.
You don't have those extreme movements
like you have in a in an equal-weighted
fund.
On the concentration concern, by tilting
away from larger and higher-priced
stocks, the Dimensional fund is reducing
concentration, but not to the same
extent as equal weighting. If your only
concern is market concentration, equal
weighting is a is a really good
solution. But that's probably not the
right problem to to solve.
Looking again at factor regressions, we
see that the Dimensional fund and the
equal-weight S&P 500 fund have had
roughly similar factor exposures, but as
expected, the Dimensional fund is not
taking a negative position on momentum
because of the way that they trade.
Going back to 2005, when the Dimensional
Core Equity One fund first launched,
both the equal-weight S&P 500 ETF and
the Dimensional fund trail an S&P 500
ETF, but the Dimensional fund does
outperform the equal-weight fund. This
was a period where large stocks with
high prices performed really well. So,
the result of the S&P 500 coming out
ahead over this period is not
surprising. Going back to 1971,
which is when backtest data start for
the S&P 500 equal-weight index,
equal weighting looks really really good
compared to the market cap-weighted S&P
500. This was a period where small cap
and value stocks performed well. Again,
we can see using multifactor regression
that the performance of the
equal-weighted fund is largely explained
by higher exposure to small cap and
value stocks with a negative
contribution from momentum. Comparing
this equal-weight result to the
backtested Dimensional US Core Equity
One Index, so to be clear, this is not a
fund anymore, this is a backtested
index,
uh it is is also a really interesting
comparison. It had roughly similar
exposure to small cap and value stocks,
a lighter negative exposure to momentum,
and it performs nearly identically to
the equal-weight S&P 500 index over the
full period with less volatility. Keep
in mind that for both of these
backtested examples, that this is
backtest data, which can be pretty
unreliable. There's a saying in finance
that you'll never see a backtest you
don't like.
They're built with the benefit of
hindsight, and they don't reflect
real-world implementation costs, but
it's still interesting to see a similar
trend to what we saw in live funds.
Exposure to smaller and cheaper stocks
and negative exposure to momentum, in
the case of the equal-weight fund,
explains most of the results.
Equal-weight indexing seems appealing
right now because high concentration in
the top stocks and high market
valuations in the US market are making
investors nervous.
That, in addition to some pretty
attractive long-term backtests, seem to
make a strong case for equal weighting.
But it comes with some baggage. Equal
weighting results in large over- and
underweights at the individual stock and
sector levels, high portfolio turnover,
and a systematic bet against momentum.
The strong past returns of equal
weighting are largely explained by tilts
towards smaller and lower-priced stocks
rather than some magic from equal
weights.
The implication for investors is is that
if you want to tilt towards smaller and
lower-priced stocks, which is a
reasonable thing to want to do, you can
do it without introducing all of the
downsides of equal weighting.
Dimensional Fund Advisors creates
products that do something like that.
They tilt towards smaller and
lower-priced stocks systematically, in
addition to a couple of other factors,
while controlling for sector exposure,
limiting portfolio turnover, and
intentionally avoiding trading against
momentum, among a whole bunch of other
interesting stuff that I've talked about
in past videos. To be clear about one
thing, Dimensional did not pay or
otherwise incentivize me to talk about
their funds in this video. My firm, PWL
Capital, does use their Canadian
products in our clients' portfolios. I
did a video a while ago explaining
Dimensional's history, which is closely
tied to the history of index funds, and
comparing their long-term performance to
comparable Vanguard index funds.